So how many of you have ever been in a cave before?
كم عدد من ذهب يوما إلى كهف؟
Okay, a few of you.
حسنا، بعضكم.
When you think of a cave, most of you think
عند تفكيرك في كهف، تتخيّل في الغالب
of a tunnel going through solid rock,
نفقا يمتدّ عبر صخرة صلبة،
and in fact, that's how most caves are.
و في الواقع معظم الكهوف هي كذلك بالفعل.
Around this half of the country,
في قرابة نصف هذا البلد،
most of your caves are made of limestone.
تتكوّن معظم الكهوف من حجر الكلس.
Back where I'm from, most of our caves are made of lava rock,
المنطقة التي آتي منها بها كهوف تكون أغلبها متكوّنة من الحمم الحجرية،
because we have a lot of volcanoes out there.
لأنّ هناك الكثير من البراكين في المنطقة.
But the caves I want to share with you today are made
لكن الكهوف التي أودّ أن أتحدث عنها اليوم تتكوّن
completely of ice, specifically glacier ice
تماما من الثلج، و بدقة الجليد الثّلجي
that's formed in the side of the tallest mountain
الذي يتكوّن على جانب أطول جبل
in the state of Oregon, called Mount Hood.
في ولاية أوريغون، المسمّى جبل هود.
Now Mount Hood's only one hour's drive from Portland,
يمكن الوصول إليه في رحلة تستغرق ساعة واحدة من مدينة بورتلاند،
the largest city in Oregon,
وهي أكبر مدينة بأوريغون،
where over two million people live.
حيث يسكن مليوني شخص.
Now the most exciting thing for a cave explorer
إنّ أكثر أمر يثير حماس مكتشف كهوف
is to find a new cave
هو العثور على كهف جديد
and be the first human to ever go into it.
وتكون واطئه للمرة الأولى على الإطلاق.
The second most exciting thing for a cave explorer
ثاني أمر يثير حماس مستكشف كهوف
is to be the first one to make a map of a cave.
هو أن يكون أول من يضع خريطة لكهف.
Now these days, with so many people hiking around,
في أيامنا هذه، و مع تزايد عدد من يمارسون تسلّق الجبال،
it's pretty hard to find a new cave,
أصبح من الصعب العثور على كهف جديد
so you can imagine how excited we were
لذا فيمكنكم تخيّل شدّة حماسنا
to find three new caves
لاكتشافنا هذه الكهوف الثلاثة
within sight of Oregon's largest city
في المنطقة القريبة لأكبر مدينة بأوريغون
and realize that they had never been explored
و إدراكنا لكونها لم تكتشف من قبل أو يتمّ
or mapped before.
وضع خرائط لها.
It was kind of like being an astronaut,
كأنّنا كنّا رائدي فضاء،
because we were getting to see things and go places
لأنّنا تمكّننا من الذهاب إلى أماكن و رؤية أمور
that no one had ever seen or gone to before.
لم يسبق لأحد رؤيتها أو الذّهاب إليها من قبل.
So what is a glacier?
ما هو الجليد؟
Well, those of you who have ever seen or touched snow,
بالنّسبة لمن رآى منكم أو لمس الثّلج،
you know that it's really light,
فأنتم تعرفون أنّه خفيف الوزن،
because it's just a bunch of tiny ice crystals clumped together, and it's mostly air.
لأنّه مجرد حفنة من البلورات الثلجية الصغيرة مكدّسة معا و نسبة كبيرة منها هواء.
If you squish a handful of snow to make a snowball,
إن جمعت حفنة منها لصنع كرة ثلجية،
it gets really small, hard and dense.
تصبح أصغر و أصلب و أكثر كثافة.
Well, on a mountain like Hood, where it snows
حسنا، في جبل مثل هود حيث يصل
over 20 feet a year,
مستوى الثّلوج 20 قدما في السنة،
it crushes the air out of it
يتمّ سحق الهواء إلى خارج الثلوج
and gradually forms it into hard blue ice.
و تتحوّل تدريجيّا إلى ثلج صلب أزرق.
Now each year, more and more ice stacks up on top of it,
وفي كل سنة، يتكدّس المزيد و المزيد من الثّلج فوقه
and eventually it gets so heavy
و في النّهاية يصبح ثقيل الوزن جدّا
that it starts to slide down the mountain
لدرجة أنّه ينزلق نحو أسفل الجبل
under its own weight,
مدفوعا بوزنه الثقيل،
forming a slow-moving river of ice.
مشكّلا نهرا من الجليد بطيء الحركة.
When ice packed like that starts to move,
عندما يبدأ الجليد في تلك الحالة بالتّحرك،
we call it a glacier, and we give it a name.
نسمّيه كتلة جليديّة و نطلق عليها اسما.
The name of the glacier these caves are formed in
اسم الكتل الجليديّة التي تشكّلت فيها هذه الكهوف
is the Sandy Glacier.
هو جليد ساندي.
Now each year, as new snow lands on the glacier,
كلّ سنة، مع هبوط مزيد من الثلوج على الجليد،
it melts in the summer sun,
تقوم شمس الصيف بتذويبها،
and it forms little rivers of water on the flow along the ice,
و تشكّل أنهارا صغيرة من المياه فوق الجليد،
and they start to melt and bore their way down through the glacier,
ثمّ تبدأ بالذوبان و تشق طريقها إلى أسفل داخل الجليد،
forming big networks of caves,
مشكّلة قنوات كبيرة من الكهوف،
sometimes going all the way down to the underlying bedrock.
قد تصل أحيانا إلى أسفل طبقة.
Now the crazy thing about glacier caves
الأمر الجنونيّ حول الكهوف الجليدية
is that each year, new tunnels form.
هو أنّ قنوات جديدة تتشكّل كلّ سنة.
Different waterfalls pop up or move around
تظهر شلالات جديدة أو تتنقّل
from place to place inside the cave.
من أماكنها داخل الكهف.
Warm water from the top of the ice
الماء الدافئ القادم من أعلى الجليد
is boring its way down,
يتجه إلى أسفل
and warm air from below the mountain
و الهواء الدافئ القادم من أسفل الجبل
actually rises up, gets into the cave,
يرتفع إلى أعلى و يدخل إلى الكهف
and melts the ceilings back taller and taller.
مذيبا الأسقف الجليدية فتزداد طولا.
But the weirdest thing about glacier caves
لكن أغرب شيء حول الكهوف الجليدية
is that the entire cave is moving,
هو كون الكهف كلّه يتنقّل
because it's formed inside a block of ice
لأنّه تشكّل فوق كتلة جليديّة
the size of a small city
بحجم مدينة صغيرة
that's slowly sliding down the mountain.
تنزلق ببطئ على منحدر جبليّ.
Now this is Brent McGregor,
هذا برينت ماك جريجور،
my cave exploration partner.
شريكي في استكشاف الكهوف.
He and I have both been exploring caves a long time
قمنا معا باستكشاف الكهوف
and we've been climbing mountains a long time,
و كنّا نتسلّق الجبال معا لمدّة طويلة من الزّمن،
but neither one of us had ever really explored a glacier cave before.
لكن ما من أحد منّا قام باستكشاف كهف جليديّ سابقا.
Back in 2011, Brent saw a YouTube video
سنة 2011، شاهد برينت فيديو على اليوتيوب
of a couple of hikers that stumbled across the entrance to one of these caves.
لمجموعة من المتسلّقين الذين وجدوا أنفسهم بالصدفة قرب مدخل إحدى هذه الكهوف.
There were no GPS coordinates for it,
لم تكن هناك إحداثيّات بنظام تحديد المواقع للمكان،
and all we knew was that it was somewhere
و كلّ ما كنّا نعرفه هو أنّه في مكان ما
out on the Sandy Glacier.
خارج جليد ساندي.
So in July of that year, we went out on the glacier,
في شهر يوليو/جويلية من نفس السنة، ذهبنا إليه
and we found a big crack in the ice.
و اكتشفنا تصدّعا كبيرا في الجليد.
We had to build snow and ice anchors
كان علينا أن نبني مراسي من الثلج و الجليد
so that we could tie off ropes and rappel down into the hole.
حتّى نستطيع ربط أحبالنا و الهبوط داخل الحفرة.
This is me looking into the entrance crevasse.
هذا أنا أنظر إلى مدخل الصّدع العميق.
At the end of this hole, we found a huge tunnel
في نهاية الفجوة، نجد نفقا كبيرا
going right up the mountain
يتّجه مباشرة إلى أعلى الجبل
underneath thousands of tons of glacier ice.
تحت آلاف من الأطنان من الجليد.
We followed this cave back for about a half mile
قمنا بالتّجول في هذا الكهف مسافة نصف ميل (805 متر)
until it came to an end,
إلى أن بلغنا نهايته،
and then with the help of our survey tools
و بالاستعانة بمعدات المسح خاصتنا
we made a three-dimensional map of the cave
قمنا بوضع خارطة ثلاثية الأبعاد للكهف
on our way back out.
في طريق خروجنا.
So how do you map a cave?
كيف يتم وضع خريطة لكهف ما؟
Well, cave maps aren't like trail maps or road maps
حسنا، خرائط الكهوف ليست خرائط مسارات أو طرقات
because they have pits and holes going to overlapping levels.
لأنّ بها حفرا و فجوات موجودة في مستويات متداخلة.
To make a cave map, you have to set up
لصنع خريطة كهف، عليك أن تعدّ
survey stations every few feet inside the cave,
محطات مسح كلّ مسافات قصيرة داخل الكهف،
and you use a laser to measure the distance between those stations.
و تستعمل ليزرا لقياس المسافة بين هذه المحطات.
Then you use a compass and an inclinometer
ثمّ يجب استعمال بوصلة و مقياس الميلان
to measure the direction the cave is headed
لمعرفة الاتجاه الذي يتجه نحوه الكهف
and measure the slope of the floor and the ceilings.
و قيس انحدار الأرضيّة و الأسقف.
Now those of you taking trigonometry,
بالنّسبة لمن يدرس منكم علم المثلثات،
that particular type of math is very useful
فإنّ ذلك الفرع من الرياضيات مفيد جدّا
for making maps like this
لوضع خرائط كهذه
because it allows you to measure heights and distances
لأنّها تسمح لك بقيس الارتفاعات و المسافات
without actually having to go there.
دون الحاجة لأن تكون هناك بالفعل.
In fact, the more I mapped and studied caves,
في الواقع كلّما درست كهوفا و وضعت خرائط لها،
the more useful I found all that math
كلما وجدت أنّ كلّ تلك الرياضيات
that I originally hated in school to be.
التي كنت أكرهها في المدرسة، مفيدة.
So when you're done surveying,
عندما تنهي المسح،
you take all this data and you punch it into a computer
تأخذ كلّ البيانات و تضعها في الحاسوب
and you find someone that can draw really well,
و تحاول إيجاد شخص يجيد الرّسم جيّدا
and you have them draft up a map
و تطلب منه وضع مسوّدة لخريطة
that looks something like this,
تكون مشابهة لهذه
and it'll show you both a bird's-eye view of the passage
و سوف تريكم المكان من وجهة نظر طائر محلّق قرب المكان
as well as a profile view of the passage,
و أيضا نظرة جانبيّ للمكان
kind of like an ant farm view.
نوعا ما كوجهة مزرعة نمل.
We named this cave Snow Dragon Cave
سميّنا هذا الكهف كهف ثلج التّنين
because it was like a big dragon sleeping under the snow.
لأنّه يشبه تنّينا ضخما نائما تحت الثّلج.
Now later this summer, as more snow melted off the glacier,
في فترة لاحقة ذلك الصيف، مع ذوبان المزيد من الثلج عن الجليد
we found more caves, and we realized they were all connected.
وجدنا المزيد من الكهوف و اكتشفنا أنّها كلّها مرتبطة.
Not long after we mapped Snow Dragon,
بعد فترة قصيرة من وضع خرائط للتّنين الثلجي،
Brent discovered this new cave not very far away.
اكتشف برانت كهفا جديدا في مكان ليس ببعيد.
The inside of it was coated with ice,
داخله كان مغطّا بالجليد،
so we had to wear big spikes on our feet called crampons
لذا فقد كان علينا ارتداء مسامير بأقدامنا تسمّى خفّا مسماريّا
so we could walk around without slipping.
حتّى نتمكن من المشي دون الوقوع.
This cave was amazing.
كان الكهف رائعا.
The ice in the ceiling was glowing blue anad green
كان الجليد بالسقف يعكس لمعانا أزرق و أخضر
because the sunlight from far above
لأنّ أشعة الشمس القادمة من فوق من بعيد
was shining through the ice and lighting it all up.
كان تشعّ من خلال الجليد و تضيؤه كلّه.
And we couldn't understand why this cave
و لم نتمكن من فهم سبب كون هذا الكهف
was so much colder than Snow Dragon
أكثر برودا من التنين الجليديّ
until we got to the end and we found out why.
إلى أن وصلنا إلى نهايته و عرفنا السبب.
There was a huge pit or shaft called a moulin
لقد كانت هناك حفرة اسطوانيّ يسمى بالطاحونة
going 130 feet straight up to the surface of the glacier.
يرتفع إلى 130 قدما (40 مترا) إلى سطح الجليد.
Cold air from the top of the mountain
الهواء البارد من أعلى الجبل
was flowing down this hole and blasting through the cave,
كان يهبّ إلى هذه الحفرة معصعصا خلال الكهف،
freezing everything inside of it.
مجمّدا كلّ ما يوجد داخله.
And we were so excited about finding this new pit,
و كنّا متحمسين جدّا بشأن اكتشاف هذه الفجوة الجديدة،
we actually came back in January the following year
و عدنا في شهر يناير من السنة الموالية
so we could be the first ones to explore it.
إذن فمن الممكن أنّنا أول من اكتشفه.
It was so cold outside,
لقد كان الداخل في غاية البرود،
we actually had to sleep inside the cave.
لقد اضطررنا للنّوم خارج الكهف.
There's our camp on the left side of this entrance room.
هذا مخيّمنا في الجانب الأيسر من المدخل.
The next morning, we climbed out of the cave
في الصباح الموالي، تسلّقنا إلى خارج الكهف
and hiked all the way to the top of the glacier,
و تسلّقنا طيلة الطريق نحو الأعلى
where we finally rigged and rappelled this pit
حتّى حفرنا هذه الفجوة
for the very first time.
للمرة الأولى.
Brent named this cave Pure Imagination,
برينت سمّى الكهف خيالا خالصا،
I think because the beautiful sights we saw in there
بسبب المناظر الخلابة فيه على ما أعتقد
were beyond what we could have ever imagined.
التي كانت تفوق ما قد نتخيله يوما.
So besides really cool ice, what else is inside these caves?
إضافة إلى الجليد البارد جدّا، ما الذي كان هناك أيضا داخل الكهوف؟
Well not too much lives in them because they're so cold
لم تكن هناك أشكال حياة كثيرة لأنّها كانت شديدة البرود
and the entrance is actually covered up with snow
و كان المدخل مغطّى بالثّلج
for about eight months of the year.
مدة 8 أشهر من السنة.
But there are some really cool things in there.
لكن هناك أمورا ممتعة جدا فيها،
There's weird bacteria living in the water
هناك بكتيريا غريبة تعيش في الماء
that actually eat and digest rocks
تأكل و تقوم بهضم الصخور
to make their own food
لصنع غذائها الخاص
to live under this ice.
للعيش تحت الثّلج.
In fact, this past summer, scientists collected
في الواقع، في الصيف الفارط قام علماء بجمع
samples of water and ice
عيّنات من الماء و الثّلج
specifically to see if things called extremophiles,
خاصة لرؤية ما يسمى بأليف الظروف القاسية،
tiny lifeforms that are evolved to live in completely hostile conditions,
وهي أشكال حياة صغيرة تطوّرت للعيش في ظروف في غاية القسوة،
might be living under the ice,
التي قد تكون موجودة تحت الجليد،
kind of like what they hope to find on the polar icecaps of Mars someday.
نفس أشكال الحياة التي يأمل العلماء في إيجادها في الأقطاب الثلجية بكوكب المريخ يوما ما.
Another really cool things is that,
هناك أمر آخر رائع وهو أنّ
as seeds and birds land on the surface of the glacier and die,
الجذور و الطيور تحطّ على سطح الجليد و تموت
they get buried in the snow
فتدفن تحت الثّلج
and gradually become part of the glacier,
و تصبح تدريجيا جزءا من الجليد،
sinking deeper and deeper into the ice.
غارقة أكثر فأكثر في الثّلج.
As these caves form and melt their way up into the ice,
وهذه الكهوف تتشكّل و تذوب في الجليد،
they make these artifacts rain down from the ceiling
و تجعل هذه الآثار تمطر من السقف
and fall onto the cave floor, where we end up finding them.
و تسقط إلى أرضية الكهف، حيث نجدها.
For example, this is a noble fir seed we found.
مثلا، وجدنا جذور شجرة الشوح الطويل هذه.
It's been frozen in the ice for over 100 years,
لقد بقيت متجمدة في الجليد طيلة 100 سنة،
and it's just now starting to sprout.
و بدأت في التبرعم الآن.
This mallard duck feather
هذه ريشة بط بريّ
was found over 1,800 feet in the back of Snow Dragon Cave.
وجدت على بعد 1800 قدم في نهاية كهف تنين الثّلج.
This duck died on the surface of the glacier long, long ago,
مات البط على سطح الكتلة الجليدية منذ وقت طويل جدّا،
and its feathers have finally made it down through over 100 feet of ice
و لقد نجى ريشه تحت 100 قدم (30.5 متر تقريبا) من الجليد
before falling inside the cave.
قبل السقوط داخل الكهف.
And this beautiful quartz crystal
وهذه بلورة كوارتز جميلة
was also found in the back of Snow Dragon.
كنّا قد وجدناها في كهف تنين الثّلج.
Even now, Brent and I find it hard to believe
حتّى الآن، لازلنا أنا و برينت نجد صعوبة في تصديق
that all these discoveries were essentially in our own backyard,
أنّ هذه الاكتشافات كانت تقريبا في باحتنا الخلفية،
hidden away, just waiting to be found.
مختبئة، تنتظر من يكتشفها.
Like I said earlier, the idea of discovering
كما قلت سابقا، فكرة الاكتشاف
in this busy world we live in
في هذا العالم المنشغل الذي نعيش فيه
kind of seems like something you can only do with space travel now,
تبدو و كأنّها أمر لا يمكن حدوثه إلاّ في السفر في الفضاء الآن،
but that's not true.
لكن الأمر ليس صحيحا.
Every year, new caves get discovered
كلّ سنة، يتم اكتشاف مزيد الكهوف الجديدة
that no one has ever been in before.
التي لم تطأها قدم من قبل.
So it's actually not too late for one of you
إذن فالأوان لم يفت بعد كي يصبح
to become a discoverer yourself.
أحدكم مستكشفا.
You just have to be willing to look
عليك فقط أن تكون عندك الرغبة في البحث
and go where people don't often go
و الذهاب إلى أماكن يندر الذهاب إليها
and focus your eyes and your mind
و تركّز بعينينك و ذهنك
to recognize the discovery when you see it,
للتّعرف على الاكتشاف عند رؤيته،
because it might be in your own backyard.
لأنّه قد يكون موجودا في باحتك الخلفيّة.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)